Hi, in this short video, we will solve a code problem together.
مرحباً، في هذا الفيديو القصير سوف نحل مسألة برمجية معاً.
The problem itself is quite elementary.
المسألة في حد ذاتها بسيطة جداً.
So the main purpose of this video is to show you the general pipeline
لذلك فإن الغرض الأساسى من هذا الفيديو هو توضيح البرنامج العام الذى يتم تطبيقه
of solving code problems in this class.
لحل المسائل البرمجية فى هذا الفصل.
The problem is called A plus B.
المسألة تسمى A + B.
In this problem, we are given two digits on the standard input and
فى هذه المسألة، معطى رقمين عن طريق الإدخال القياسى Standard Input.
our goal is to output their sum on the standard output.
و هدفنا هو أن ننتج مجموعهما عن طريق الإنتاج القياسى Standard Output.
You can see two sample tests here on the page.
تستطيع أن ترى نموذجين اختبار على الصفحة.
For example, if the input for your program consists of the integers 3 and
على سبيل المثال، لو كانت المدخلات للبرنامج تتكون من الأعداد الصحيحة 3 و
2, then your program should output 5.
2، حينئذٍ فإن برنامجك يجب أن يخرج 5.
If, on the other hand, the input consists of two integers 7 and
لو كان المدخلات تتكون من العددين الصحيحين 7 و
9, then your program is supposed to output 16, of course.
9، حينئذٍ فإن برنامجك من المفترض أن يخرج 16 بالطبع.
The next section consists of three Starter files.
القسم التالى يتكون من 3 ملفات إبتدائية.
Which in this particular case are actually solutions, not just starter files.
و لكنهم في هذه الحالة الخاصة حلول و ليس فقط ملفات ابتدائية.
So the files are for programming languages Python, Java, and C++.
و بالتالى فإن هذه الملفات للغات البرمجة بايثون، جافا و سى بلس بلس.
Finally the last section contains an instruction
أخيراً فإن القسم الأخير يحتوى على تعليمات
consisting of four steps on how to solve this problem.
تتكون من 4 خطوات في كيفية حل هذه المسألة.
So let's go through these four steps together.
لذلك فلنستعرض هذه الخطوات معا.
The first step is to download one of the starter files.
أول خطوة هي أن تحمل إحدى الملفات الابتدائية.
For this, let's select the C++ starter file, and let's download it.
لهذا, سنختار الملف الابتدائي لسي بلس بلس، وسنقوم بتحميله.
Okay.
حسناً
Now the file is here and let's take a look inside.
الآن الملف هنا و هيا نلقى نظرة على ما بداخله.
So, this is a very simple solution which, first, creates three variables.
هذا حل بسيط جداً هو أولاً، ينشئ 3 متغيرات.
Then it reads a and b from the standard input.
و بعد ذلك يقوم بقراءة a , b من الإدخال القياسي standard input.
Then it computes the sum.
و بعد ذلك يحسب المجموع.
And then finally it outputs the sum on the standard output.
و بعد ذلك في النهاية ينتج المجموع عن طريق الإنتاج القياسي.
So to run this program we first need to compile it.
لذلك من أجل تشغيل هذا البرنامج نحن بحاجة فقط إلى عمل ترجمة للبرنامج.
So this is the second step of our instruction.
و هذه هى الخطوة الثانية فى التعليمات.
For this we highly recommend to use the same
من أجل هذا نوصى بشدة أن تستخدم نفس
compiler flags that are shown on this page.
علامات المترجم Compiler Flags كما هى موضحة فى هذه الصفحة.
This will ensure that your program behaves in the same way
هذا سوف يؤكد أن برنامجك يتصرف بنفس الطريقة
on the testing system and on your local machine.
على نظام الاختبار وعلى جهازك المحلي.
So in this case let's just copy the flags and
لذلك فى هذه الحالة دعونا فقط ننسخ العلامات Flags و
use it to compile our program.
و نستخدمها لكى نترجم برنامجنا.
So this produced an executable file a.out and we can now run it.
و فى هذا الجزء أنت تستخدم ملف تنفيذى a.out و يمكننا الآن تشغيله.
Let's give this program for example 2 and 3.
دعونا نعطى هذا البرنامج على سبيل المثال 2 و 3.
So the output is 5.
لذا فإن الناتج يكون 5.
Well, one more test.
حسناً، لنجرى إختباراً آخر.
9 and 4, the output is 13 as expected.
9 و 4, الناتج 13 كما هو متوقع.
So far, so good.
حتى الآن، جيد جداً
And now the next step is to actually submit this solution to this problem.
و الآن الخطوة القادمة هي أن نقوم فعلياً بتسليم الحل لهذه المسألة
Let's go to my submission tab.
دعونا نذهب إلى تسليماتى فالأعلى.
Press create submission, then replace a file by this .cpp file
أضغط على إنشاء تسليم ثم بعد ذلك أستبدل الملف بملف ال CPP لديك
And press the Submit button.
ثم أضغط على زر تسليم.
So after a while, the testing system shows
بعد لحظة يعرض نظام الاختبار
that our solution passed all the tests, which is quite satisfactory.
أن الحل لدينا قد أجتاز جميع الاختبارات وهذا مُرضى تماماً.
In this particular case, the grader output is empty,
في هذه الحالة الخاصة فإن ناتج التقييم فارغ.
meaning that there is no error message in this case.
مما يعنى أنه ليس هناك رسالة خطأ في هذه الحالة.
To illustrate it one more time, let me repeat the whole procedure quickly for
لتوضيح ذلك أكثر دعوني أكرر الإجراء بكامله سريعاً
the Python programming language.
للغة البرمجة بايثون.
So we first download the starter Python file.
لذلك أولاً نقوم بتحميل الملف الابتدائي لبايثون.
Let's take a look at what is inside.
دعونا نلقى نظرة على ما بداخله.
So the program is again very simple as expected.
البرنامج بسيط جداً كما هو المتوقع.
So we just take a and be from the standard input and we output the sum of a and b.
نحن فقط نأخذ a  وb من الإدخال القياسي و نخرج حاصل جمع a  وb
Now we need to run this program for
نحن نحتاج الآن إلى تشغيل هذا البرنامج
this you might want to go to this available programming languages page.
و لهذا قد تحتاج إلى الذهاب إلى صفحة لغات البرمجة المتاحة.
Again just to check how we run Python scripts so
مرة أخرى كيف نفحص كيف يمكننا تشغيل تلك المخطوطات لذلك
we just use Python, Python 3.
نحن فقط نستخدم بايثون3.
So let's do this.
لذلك دعونا نفعل ذلك.
For example 4, 4 and the output is 8 which is as expected.
على سبيل المثال 4 و4 الناتج 8 كما هو متوقع.
So let's just go ahead and submit this solution.
لذلك دعونا فقط نمضى قُدماً .و نسلم هذا الحل
So you go to the my submission tab, you press the Create Submission button and
لذلك تذهب إلى علامة التبويب تسليماتى هنا أضغط على زر إنشاء تسليم و
then you replace this file by APlusB.py.
و قم باستبدال هذا الملف بملف APlusB.py
So when the file is uploaded, you finally press the Submit button.
و حين يتم رفع الملف في النهاية  قم بالضغط على زر التسليم.
So in a few seconds, this solution will be accepted by the testing system.
و في غضون ثواني قليلة سوف يتم قبول الحل عن طريق نظام الاختبار.
Well this wasn't very challenging, right?
حسناً لم يكن هذا ليس تحدياً كبيراً، أليس كذلك ؟
In the next video we will see a much more
في الفيديو القادم سوف نرى
interesting example of a computational problem.
مثالاً أكثر متعة لمسألة حاسوبية.
For this problem we will start with a naive solution.
فى هذه المسألة سوف نبدأ بحل
We will submit this solution to a testing system to figure out that it is buggy
و سوف نقوم بتسليم الحل إلى نظام الاختبار لنكتشف أنه به عيوب
actually.
فى الواقع.
That there is a bug.
يوجد به ثغرة (خطأ برمجي)
So we will fix this bug, submit it again, to find out that our solution is slow.
لذلك سوف نحل هذه الثغرة و نسلمه مرة أخرى فنكتشف أن حلنا هذا بطيء
We will get a time limit exceeded feedback message from the testing system.
سنكتشف انه قد تجاوز الوقت المحدد عن طريق رسالة من نظام الاختبار
Meaning that for large data sets it works in more than one second, for example.
وذلك يعني أنه للبيانات الكبيرة يعمل البرنامج في أكثر من ثانية واحدة، على سبيل المثال.
So this will require us to come up with a much, more faster solution.
و لذلك سوف يتطلب ذلك منّا أن نأتي بحل أسرع.
We will implement it, submit it to the system,
سوف نقوم بتنفيذه وتسليمه إلى النظام
again, to find out that it is still buggy.
مرة أخرى، لنجد أنه لا زال به عيوب
We will use stress testing to locate the bug, to fix it, and
سوف نستخدم إختبار مشدد لتحديد الثرة، حلها و
to finally submit a correct solution to the system which will pass all the tests.
وفي النهاية نسلم حل صحيح إلى النظام و الذي سوف يجتاز جميع الاختبارات.